A Guide to the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial records FA061
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Appropriations, 1917-1949; 3
  - Appropriations - General Education, 3_09
    - American Council on Education - International Education, 1923-1928 (Box 104, Folder 1047)
    - American School of Classical Studies - Athens, 1922-1931 (Box 104, Folder 1048)
      Advisory Committee-LSRM. Agora. Edward Capps.
    - American School of Classical Studies - Athens, 1922-1931 (Box 104, Folder 1049)
    - American School of Classical Studies - Athens, 1922-1931 (Box 104, Folder 1050)
    - American School of Classical Studies - Athens - Miscellaneous (Box 104, Folder 1051)
    - American Universities, 1928 (Box 104, Folder 1052)
    - Bureau of Occupations, 1923-1924 (Box 104, Folder 1053)
      Vocational service - opportunity for high school women and college grads.
    - Bureau of Vocational Information, 1921-1926 (Box 104, Folder 1054)
      Special studies, training for women.
    - Bureau of Vocational Information - Secretarial Study, 1923-1927 (Box 104, Folder 1055)
    - Bureau of Vocational Information - The Woman Secretary (Box 105, Folder 1056)
    - Bureau of Vocational Information - The Woman Secretary (Box 105, Folder 1057)
    - Bureau of Vocational Information - Training Report, 1923-1925 (Box 105, Folder 1058)
    - Cooperative Education Association of Virginia, 1923-1928 (Box 105, Folder 1059)
      Demonstration work, support development of State Board of Health, compulsory education.
    - Cooperative Education Association of Virginia, 1923-1928 (Box 105, Folder 1060)
    - Department of Public Instruction - Geneva, 1925-1927 (Box 105, Folder 1061)
      Institute of International Studies.
    - Department of Public Instruction - Geneva, 1925-1927 (Box 105, Folder 1062)
    - George Peabody College - Vanderbilt University, 1925-1926 (Box 105, Folder 1063)
      Education for social welfare.
    - Human Studies Survey - Young, 1925-1928 (Box 105, Folder 1064)
      Humanities.
    - Human Studies Survey - Young - Report (Box 105, Folder 1065)
    - Institute of International Education, 1923-1937 (Box 106, Folder 1066)
      LSRM-RF. Information and advice to American and foreign students; general background information.
    - Institute of Social and Religious Research, 1923-1926 (Box 106, Folder 1067)
      Survey of educational conditions abroad for American children.
    - International School at Geneva, 1925-1927 (Box 106, Folder 1068)
      Multiple language school, method and program of international education; general background information.
    - Library Science School, 1925 (Box 106, Folder 1069)
    - National Community Foundation, 1927 (Box 106, Folder 1070)
    - National University Extension Association, 1924 (Box 106, Folder 1071)
    - National University Presses, 1922-1927 (Box 106, Folder 1072)
    - Near East College, 1921-1926 (Box 106, Folder 1073)
      Advisory Committee. For girls at Constantinople. Joint appeal with Robert College and American University of Beirut. George Plimpton.
    - Near East College, 1921-1926 (Box 106, Folder 1074)
    - New York City Schools, 1921 (Box 106, Folder 1075)
    - North Carolina State Board of Charities - School Attendance, 1927-1931 (Box 106, Folder 1076)
      LSRM-SF. Compulsory school attendance work, demonstration in several counties how difficulties met.
    - North China Union Language School, 1920-1925 (Box 106, Folder 1077)
      To teach "things Chinese", building and equipment. W. B. Pettus, Roger S. Greene.
    - Polish School of Adult Education, 1926-1929 (Box 106, Folder 1078)
    - Progressive Education Association, 1926-1928 (Box 106, Folder 1079)
    - Public Education Association, 1925-1926 (Box 106, Folder 1080)
    - Russian Student Fund, 1922-1924 (Box 106, Folder 1081)
      LSRM-RF. Scholarships and loans for Russian students in United States.
    - Russian Student Fund, 1925-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1082)
    - Russian Student Fund, 1925-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1083)
    - Russian Student Fund - Reports (Box 107, Folder 1084)
    - Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1921-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1085)
      LSRM-RF. Help Southern girls get an education, become self-supporting; counsel and guidance; general background information. Orie F. Hatcher. Jackson Davis.
    - Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1921-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1086)
    - Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1921-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1087)
    - Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1921-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1088)
    - Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1921-1929 (Box 107, Folder 1089)
    - Southern Woman's Educational Alliance - Reports (Box 108, Folder 1090)
    - "Location of Virginia Girls applying for Scholarships administered by the Southern Women's Educational Alliance", MAP (Quantity 1) (Drawer C 2, Folder 1)
      separated from: Box 108, folder 1090.
    - Southern Woman's Educational Alliance - Reports (Box 108, Folder 1091)
    - Southern Woman's Educational Alliance - Reports (Box 108, Folder 1092)
    - Southern Woman's Educational Alliance - Reports (Box 108, Folder 1093)
    - Southern Woman's Educational Alliance - Bulletins and Clippings (Box 108, Folder 1094)
    - Stephens Junior College, 1923-1929 (Box 108, Folder 1095)
    - Stephens Junior College, 1923-1929 (Box 108, Folder 1096)
    - Tennessee Wesleyan College, 1928 (Box 109, Folder 1097)
    - Thompson, Wallace, 1923-1926 (Box 109, Folder 1098)
    - Tsuda College, 1923-1930 (Box 109, Folder 1099)
      Advisory Committee-LSRM. Tokyo, for women, Christian non-denominational; earthquake, Jerome D. Greene.
    - Tsuda College, 1923-1930 (Box 109, Folder 1100)
    - Union Academy of Belleville, 1923 (Box 109, Folder 1101)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1924-1931 (Box 109, Folder 1102)
      Demonstrations.
    - University of Chicago Press, 1924-1931 (Box 109, Folder 1103)
    - University of Louvaine, 1923 (Box 109, Folder 1104)
    - University of Missouri - Pamphlets (Box 109, Folder 1105)
    - University of North Carolina Press, 1924-1926 (Box 109, Folder 1106)
      Scientific and educational material of merit; Journal; general background information. Arthur W. Page, Louis Round Wilson, Howard Odum.
    - University of North Carolina Press, 1924-1926 (Box 109, Folder 1107)
    - University of North Carolina Press, 1927-1928 (Box 110, Folder 1108)
    - University of North Carolina Press, 1927-1928 (Box 110, Folder 1109)
    - University of North Carolina Press - Reports (Box 110, Folder 1110)
    - "World Review", 1928 (Box 110, Folder 1111)
  - Appropriations - Miscellaneous, 3_10
    This subseries contains folders for individual appropriations as well as general subject information, declinations, and particular individuals. Material included consists of correspondence, charts, maps, books, clippings, reports, pamphlets, and photographs. Books have been filed in the Archives library, and photographs have been included in the photograph collection.
    - American Scandinavian Foundation, 1926-1927 (Box 111, Folder 1112)
      General background information. Student exchange, information service, publications.
    - The Commonwealth Fund, 1921-1925 (Box 111, Folder 1113)
    - Curie Radium Fund, 1921-1922 (Box 111, Folder 1114)
      Radium for her visit.
    - Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research, 1926-1930 (Box 111, Folder 1115)
      LSRM-SF. Uniform Criminal Statistics, Under Committee of International Association of Police Chiefs. Leut. D. Upson, J. Edgar Hoover, William P. Rutledge.
    - Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research, 1926-1930 (Box 111, Folder 1116)
    - Housing in American University, 1924 (Box 111, Folder 1117)
      Advisory Committee. Financing corporation to purchase second mortgages. H. J. Thorkelson.
    - Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency, 1924-1927 (Box 111, Folder 1118)
    - League of Nations, 1924-1928 (Box 111, Folder 1119)
    - National American Council, 1922 (Box 111, Folder 1120)
    - National Committee on Prisons and Prison Labor, 1922 (Box 111, Folder 1121)
    - National Conference of Juvenile Agencies, 1924 (Box 111, Folder 1122)
    - National Council for the Prevention of War, 1925 (Box 111, Folder 1123)
    - National Information Bureau, 1922-1929 (Box 111, Folder 1124)
      General background information, investigate work of organizations engaged in social, civic, or philanthropic work supported at least in part by voluntary contributions, special studies.
    - National Information Bureau, 1922-1929 (Box 111, Folder 1125)
    - National Motion Picture League, 1922-1923 (Box 111, Folder 1126)
    - National Research Council - Paper Study, 1928 (Box 111, Folder 1127)
    - National Society of Penal Information, 1924 (Box 111, Folder 1128)
    - National Women's Trade Union, 1922-1923 (Box 111, Folder 1129)
    - New York Public Library - Survey, 1920-1923 (Box 111, Folder 1130)
      Reference department.
    - New York Public Library - Survey Reports (Box 111, Folder 1131)
    - New York University, 1924 (Box 112, Folder 1132)
    - New York Zoological Society, 1923-1925 (Box 112, Folder 1133)
    - Nichols, W. A., 1927 (Box 112, Folder 1134)
    - Northwestern University, 1923-1929 (Box 112, Folder 1135)
    - Oberlin College, 1924-1927 (Box 112, Folder 1136)
    - Ohio State University, 1925-1928 (Box 112, Folder 1137)
    - Personnel Research Federation, 1925-1928 (Box 112, Folder 1138)
    - Princeton University, 1923-1926 (Box 112, Folder 1139)
    - Princeton University Press, 1924 (Box 112, Folder 1140)
    - Rosenwald Fund, 1923-1928 (Box 112, Folder 1141)
    - Russell Sage Foundation, 1924-1928 (Box 112, Folder 1142)
    - Russian Libraries, 1925-1926 (Box 112, Folder 1143)
    - Stanford University, 1924-1929 (Box 112, Folder 1144)
    - Stanford University Press, 1927 (Box 112, Folder 1145)
    - Stein, Ludwig, 1924 (Box 112, Folder 1146)
    - Student Advisors, 1924 (Box 112, Folder 1147)
    - Taquzadeh, S. H., 1926 (Box 112, Folder 1148)
    - University of Mexico, 1928 (Box 112, Folder 1149)
    - University of Puerto Rico, 1928 (Box 112, Folder 1150)
    - University of Rochester, 1926-1927 (Box 112, Folder 1151)
    - University of Washington, 1927-1929 (Box 112, Folder 1152)
    - Valyi, Felix, 1928 (Box 112, Folder 1153)
    - Welwyn Garden City - Brochure (Box 112, Folder 1154)
    - Wahlin, Nils, 1928 (Box 112, Folder 1155)
    - Women's International League, 1925 (Box 112, Folder 1156)
    - Women's National Farm and Garden Association, 1919 (Box 112, Folder 1157)
    - Woods, James, 1923-1924 (Box 112, Folder 1158)
    - World Society for International Friendship, 1924 (Box 112, Folder 1159)
- Finances, 1918-1932; 4
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains financial information as well as ledgers, journals, cash books, analyses, and registers.
  The following LSRM records are located in JDR financial material: Appropriations (with extracts from minutes for Executive Committee), June 30, 1922-March 26, 1925; Appropriations "No. 1," December 31, 1918-February 24, 1922; Appropriations "No. 2," February 14, 1922-February 7, 1924
  - Audits, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Audits, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Classified Appropriations, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Classified Appropriations, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Comptrollers Reports, 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Finance Committee, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1919-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial Procedure (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial Reports, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Financial Reports, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Financial Reports, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Income Tax, 1924-1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Liquidation, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Retiring Allowance, 1921-1923 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rockefeller, John D. - Gifts, 1918-1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Securities, 1918-1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tax Exemption, 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Expenditures, 1918-1928 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Administrative Appropriations, 1925-1927 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Administrative Appropriations, 1925-1927 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Administrative Appropriations, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Appropriations Analysis, 1923-April 1926 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Appropriations Analysis (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Closed Accounts (A-H) (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Closed Accounts (I-Z) (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Closed Accounts (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Spelman Fund Allocation of Resources (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Fellowships Analysis - Social Sciences (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Fellowships Analysis - Child Study (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Controlling Ledger, 1924-1928 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - General Ledger, 1918-1919 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Journal, 1918-1919 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Journal, 1918-1919 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Journal, 1926-1929 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Ledger, 1923-1929 (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - Journal, 1923-1926 (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - Coupon Book, 1924-1928 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - Journal, 1922-1925 (Box 14A, Folder 39)
  - Journal, 1926-1927 (Box 14A, Folder 40)
  - Journal, 1928-1932 (Box 14A, Folder 41)
  - Securities Ledger #3, 1925-1929 (Box 14B, Folder 42)
    General note
    Cover says 1925, 1926.
  - Securities Ledger #2, 1919-1929 (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - Cash Book, January 1923-February 1926 (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - Cash Book, March 1926-January 1929 (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - Combination Cash Book, Journal and Ledger, 1918-1925 (Box 16, Folder 46)
  - Voucher Register, May 1, 1926-June 30, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 47)
  - Voucher Register, July-December 1927 (Box 17, Folder 48)
  - Voucher Register, 1928 (Box 18, Folder 49)
- Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial photographs, 1916-1929; 1016; 0.4 Cubic Feet; 111 prints
  Biographical / Historical
  The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was incorporated in October 1918, for general philanthropic purposes. It was not geographically limited and indeed was international, especially in its early emphasis on emergency relief. A memorial to Laura Spelman Rockefeller, the first thought for a program was the welfare of women and children, but philanthropy is not easily granted along divisions of age or sex and so for the first few years of the Memorial's existence the program was fluid. W. S. Richardson was the main executive during the years 1918-1922. The Memorial worked through John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s office then, and many of the Memorial files were interwoven with other office files.
  In 1922 Beardsley Ruml became director of the Memorial and a long-range program was developed. Appropriations were still made in the areas of leisure, public health, and emergency relief, but from 1922 through the end of the Memorial's independent existence, the social sciences and welfare, child study and parent education, and interracial relations became primary interests. Research was sponsored, but not as an end unto itself; grants were made for demonstrations, concrete applications of newly gained knowledge. The aim of the entire program was to achieve concrete improvement in the conditions of life and to contribute realistically to public welfare.
  On January 3, 1929, the Memorial consolidated with The Rockefeller Foundation and became its division of Social Sciences. A final grant of $10,000,000 was made to the Spelman Fund of New York, an independently incorporated board, to administer some appropriations in child study, parent education, and interracial relations. The Spelman Fund went on to continue the Memorial's fledgling interest in public administration as its main emphasis.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply.
  Photographs
  - League of Red Cross Societies - Junior Red Cross, 1920s; 2 prints (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Junior Red Cross manual training course for teachers, Yugoslavia.
    Removed from Series 3.1 - Appropriations - Public Health, Box 2, Folders 17-21
  - New York Tuberculosis Association, 1920-1928; 9 prints (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Classrooms, children, diseases, tuberculosis, crafts, trade skills.
    Removed from Series 3.1 - Appropriations - Public Health, Box 4, Folders 48-49
  - Emergency Relief - Russian Zemstvos, 1916-1929; 17 prints (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Zemstvos, war, children, schools.
    Removed from Series 3.3 - Appropriations - Emergency Relief, Box 9, Folders 108-110
  - American Association of Museums - Yosemite, 1924-1925; 4 prints (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Museums, construction.
    Removed from Series 3.4 - Appropriations - Leisure, Box 11, Folders 121-122
  - YMCA College, Chicago, 1924; 3 prints (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Schools, gymnasiums, classrooms, Young Men's Christian Association.
    Removed from Series 3.4 - Appropriations - Leisure, Box 19, Folders 206-208
  - National Research Council - Deaf Projects, 1922; 2 prints (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Removed from Series 3.6 - Appropriations - Social Studies, Box 58, Folders 624-628
  - Emergency Relief - Near East, 1921-1922; 32 prints (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Refugees, children, orphanages, war.
    Removed from Series 3.3 - Appropriations - Emergency Relief, Box 8, Folders 100-103 and Box 9, Folder 104
  - Emergency Relief - Near East, 1921-1923; 10 prints (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Children, orphanages, refugees, war, schools, trade skills.
  - Neighborhood Teacher's Association, 1919-1929; 6 prints (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Trade skills, weaving, classrooms, libraries, holidays.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 84, Folders 881-890.
  - City Housing Corporation, New York City, 1924; 1 print (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Buildings.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 82, Folder 860 - Housing Situation in New York City.
  - People's Institute, New York City, 1919-1924; 11 prints (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Community work, weaving.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 85, Folder 898 and Box 86, Folders 899-901.
  - Boy Scouts of America - Negro, 1927; 1 print (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Segregation, clubs.
    Removed from Series 3.8 - Appropriations - Interracial Relations, Box 96, Folders 969-971.
  - Negro Health - West Virginia, 1925; 2 prints (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Segregation, hospitals, insanity.
    Removed from Series 3.8 - Appropriations - Interracial Relations, Box 100, Folder 1017.